MENG WANG

mengwang@ece.ubc.ca 4025 Fred Kaiser Building, 2332 Main Mall Vancouver, BC, Canada V6T 1Z4

SUMMARY

I am currently a 4th-year Ph.D. candidate in Computer Engineering at the University of British Columbia, where my research focuses on practical quantum computing for the NISQ era and beyond. My academic journey has involved building advanced quantum circuit simulators and optimizing the execution efficiency of variational quantum algorithms. During my previous internship at Pacific Northwest National Laboratory, I gained valuable experience in high-performance computing for quantum simulations and also engaged in interdisciplinary collaboration with experts in Chemistry and Physics.

EDUCATION

The University of British Columbia

Advisor: Dr.Prashant Nair

September 2020 - Present

Vancouver, BC, Canada

BASc in Computer Engineering

The University of British Columbia

Graduated with Distinction

September 2017 - June 2020

Vancouver, BC, Canada

Associate of Science

Langara College

September 2015 - July 2017 Vancouver, BC, Canada

AWARDS

Faculty of Applied Science Graduate Award

The annual award, subject to annual review and criteria fulfillment.

APSC Capstone Faculty Award

May 2020, UBC

2021, 2022, 2023, UBC

Dean's Honour List

Jun~2019,~UBC

Special Progressing Award

Feb 2016, Langara College

Entrance Scholarship

Jul 2015, Langara College

CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

1. ASPLOS'24

Meng Wang, Bo Fang, Ang Li, and Prashant Nair

 $Red\mbox{-}QAOA \hbox{:}\ Efficient\ Variational\ Optimization\ through\ Circuit\ Reduction$

International Conference on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems, 2024

ARXIV PREPRINTS

1. **Meng Wang**, Swamit Tannu, and Prashant Nair.

TQSim: a case for reuse-focused tree-based quantum circuit simulation

 arXiv preprint arXiv :2203.13892

2. Chenxu Liu, **Meng Wang**, Samuel A. Stein, Yufei Ding, and Ang Li

Quantum Memory: A Missing Piece in Quantum Computing Units
arXiv preprint arXiv:2309.14432

3. Fei Hua, **Meng Wang**, Gushu Li, Bo Peng, Chenxu Liu, Muqing Zheng, Samuel A. Stein, Yufei Ding, Eddy Z Zhang, Travis Humble, and Ang Li.

QASMTrans: A QASM-based Quantum Transpiler Framework for NISQ Devices
arXiv preprint arXiv:2308.07581

4. Ang Li, Chenxu Liu, Samuel Stein, In-Saeng Suh, Muqing Zheng, **Meng Wang**, Yue Shi, Bo Fang, Martin Roetteler, and Travis Humble.

**TANQ-Sim: Tensorcore Accelerated Noisy Quantum System Simulation via QIR on Perl-

mutter HPC

arXiv preprint arXiv:2404.13184

WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS

1. QCS'23 Meng Wang, Fei Hua, Chenxu Liu, Nicholas Bauman, Karol Kowalski, Daniel Claudino, Travis Humble, Prashant Nair, Ang Li

Enabling Scalable VQE Simulation on Leading HPC Systems

The International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage, and Analysis Workshop: Quantum Computing Softwares, 2023.

2. **QCS'23** Fei Hua, **Meng Wang**, Gushu Li, Bo Peng, Chenxu Liu, Muqing Zheng, Samuel A. Stein, Yufei Ding, Eddy Z Zhang, Travis Humble, and Ang Li.

QASMTrans: A QASM Quantum Transpiler Framework for NISQ Devices

The International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage, and Analysis Workshop: Quantum Computing Softwares, 2023.

3. QCCC'23 Meng Wang, Bo Fang, Ang Li, and Prashant Nair

Efficient QAOA Optimization using Directed Restarts and Graph Lookup

The Second International Workshop on Quantum Classical Cooperative Computing.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Pacific Northwest National Laboratory

Ph.D. Research Intern. Mentor: Ang Li, Bo Fang

October 2022 - August 2023 Richland, WA, USA

- Participated in developing simulation frameworks leveraging leading HPC systems including Frontier, Summit, and Perlmutter to simulate large-scale quantum circuits on GPU clusters. The simulation framework is open-sourced at https://github.com/pnnl/NWQ-Sim.
- Led research improving the efficiency of classical optimization in Quantum Approximated Optimization Algorithm (QAOA), yielding two publications: Red-QAOA (accepted at **ASPLOS'24**) proposing a circuit reduction technique, and INFORMR (in progress for **ISCA'24**) introducing an informed restart approach.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant at UBC

CPEN 312 - Digital Systems and Microcomputers

CPSC 322 - Introduction to Artificial Intelligence

APSC 160 - Introduction to Computation in Engineering Design

CPEN 411 - Computer Architecture

CPSC 340 - Machine Learning and Data Mining

Vancouver, BC, Canada

January 2024 - April 2024

July 2022 - August 2022

January 2022 - April 2022

September 2021 - December 2021

January 2021 - April 2021

SKILLS

Programming skills:

Verilog, C, C++, CUDA, HIP, MPI, Java, Python, ARMv7 Assembly, Racket.

Software Packages:

Qiskit, Qulacs.

Hardware:

System-on-Chip (SoC) FPGA, Raspberry Pi, Arduino.